<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Life | Wakatta!]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.wakatta.jp/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.wakatta.jp/"/>
  <updated>2012-03-15T12:59:19+09:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.wakatta.jp/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Frédéric Dumont]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It has been a bad year for geniuses...]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.wakatta.jp/blog/2011/10/25/it-has-been-a-bad-year-for-geniuses-dot-dot-dot/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-25T11:45:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.wakatta.jp/blog/2011/10/25/it-has-been-a-bad-year-for-geniuses-dot-dot-dot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It has been a bad year, a bad month even, for computer geniuses: <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_jobs">Steve Jobs</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dennis_Ritchie">Dennis Ritchie</a>, and now <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_McCarthy_%28computer_scientist%29">John McCarthy</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><blockquote><p>Lisp has jokingly been called "the most intelligent way to misuse a computer". I think that description is a great compliment because it transmits the full flavor of liberation: it has assisted a number of our most gifted fellow humans in thinking previously impossible thoughts.</p><footer><strong>Edsger Dijkstra</strong><cite>CACM 15:10</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>It is hard to speculate what the world would have looked like without them.</p>

<p>Certainly, people were doing exciting work at <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PARC_%28company%29">Xerox PARC</a> in Paolo Alto but it was Steve Jobs who turned these ideas into a commercial success. And then he went on and did it again with other interesting but not quite polished ideas, such as selling music on the Internet, or tablet computers.</p>

<p>Dennis Ritchie invented not just another language (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_language">C</a>), but a new way to teach languages in his book "<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_C_Programming_Language">The C Programming Language</a>", as well as a different breed of operating systems (the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix">UNIX</a> family).</p>

<p>And John McCarthy, through <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisp_%28programming_language%29">Lisp</a>, not only introduced automatic memory management, but allowed other smart people to think differently about programing and expressivity. Today's many languages own much of their syntax to C (unfortunately), but most of them derive their power from ideas first dreamed in Lisp.</p>

<p>"Think different", for them, was clearly more than just a slogan.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, it is the nature computer history that most of the giants are now reaching an age when obituaries are getting more likely, and another birthday party slightly less so.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
